Guide to the Carlo Naya Photograph Albums of Venice, 1860s-1870s RL.11356
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carlo Naya photograph albums of Venice
1860s-1870s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Naya, Carlo
RL.11356
3 Linear Feet 4 bound volumes; 92 albumen photographs Volumes: 18 1/2 x 15 1/4 inches; Prints: 10 5/8 x 13 7/8 inches
Four cloth-bound souvenir albums house 92 oversize mounted albumen prints of Venetian landmarks, taken by notable photographer Carlo Naya during the 1860s and perhaps into the 1870s. Handwritten captions are expressed in Italian with some English terms, and are transcribed exactly as they appear. Nearly all the images measure 10 5/8 x 13 7/8 inches, and almost all bear the studio negative number. Subjects include well-known landmarks of Venice, including churches, palaces, canals, bridges, and piazzas, along with city monuments and statuary such as the Winged Lion of St. Mark. Other images show interior details such as tombs, bas-reliefs, altars, and grand staircases. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
92 albumen prints in four bound volumes
Biographical / Historical
Carlo Naya was a noted Italian photographer born in 1816 in Tronzano Vercellese, a small town near Torino in the Piedmont region. He studied law in Pisa but soon took to photography. First operating in various places as a daguerreotypist, he moved to Venice in 1857 on the death of his brother, and he began working with photographer and printer Carlo Ponti; after a dispute with Ponti, Naya opened his own studio and the two became chief rivals. Naya later opened a larger studio on Piazza San Marco, and achieved international reknown as an architectural and scenic photographer. Using Naya's large stock of negatives of Venetian landmarks, his studio assembled fine souvenir albums for admirers of the city. Naya died on May 29, 1882, in Venice. His wife and her second husband continued to operate the studio until it closed in 1918. (Source: Encyclopedia of Nineteenth-Century Photography, 2008.)
Arrangement
Prints are described in this collection guide according to their sequence in the albums.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Carlo Naya photograph albums of Venice were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Content Description
These four bound albums house 92 oversize albumen prints showing images of Venetian architecture and artworks taken by notable photographer Carlo Naya during the 1860s and perhaps into the 1870s. The images were secured using the wet-collodion process on large glass plate negatives.
The cloth-bound albums measure 18 1/2 x 15 1/4 inches and each contains just over 20 prints mounted on hinged boards. The albums bear the English title "Venice" on the spines and covers, and are numbered I-IV. Album four reveals the large signature of a former owner - J.E. (John Edwin) Chase, an art collector and amateur naturalist of Holyoke, Massachusetts.
Subjects favored by Naya for these albums are the churches, palaces, canals, bridges, and piazzas of Venice, along with city monuments and statuary such as the Winged Lion of St. Mark and the equestrian statue of Bartolomeo Colleoni. The photographer's focus is on the elements of design and light; the few small human figures present in most images are included for purposes of scale. Featured sites include: the Palazzo Ducale; Piazza San Marco and the Basilica di San Marco; the Bridge of Sighs (Ponte dei Sospiri); the Gran Canale; and the church of SS. Giovanni and Paolo. Many images show interior details such as tombs (Titian and several Doges of Venice), bas-reliefs, altars, and grand staircases. In short, albums such as these display the subjects most sought-after by a knowledgeable tourist, and may have served as visual encyclopedias for educational institutions.
Nearly all the prints measure approximately 10 5/8 x 13 7/8 inches, each mounted on card stock with a handwritten caption below, the photographer's blind-stamp from his Riva Schiavoni studio, and the studio's negative number, which appears in the image. The captions are expressed in Italian with some English terms, and have been transcribed exactly as they appear, with a few errors retained. Only one sequence of images bears a date - 1865. There is a handful of prints with no negative numbers - these have been assigned an identification number starting with "UN." A few prints are signed by Naya (or Naija, as it is sometimes written).
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Architecture -- Italy -- Venice; Church buildings -- Italy -- Venice -- Pictorial works; Palaces -- Italy -- Venice -- Pictorial works; Photographers -- Italy -- Venice; Venice (Italy) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works; Venice (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Albumen prints; Black-and-white photographs; Photograph albums; Viewbooks; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Original Prints, 1; 4 bound volumes; 92 albumen prints
  - Piazza San Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0048)
    Scope and Contents
    From Album I, page 1
    Original negative number: 48
  - Campanile Loggia No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0025)
    From Album I, page 2
    Original negative number: 25
  - Campanile Loggia No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0045)
    From Album I, page 3
    Original negative number: 45
  - Piazza San Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0055)
    From Album I, page 4
    Original negative number: 55
  - Flag-Staff Pedestal, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0084)
    From Album I, page 5
    Original negative number: 84
  - Procuratie Vecchia, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0160)
    From Album I, page 6
    Original negative number: 160
  - Torre dell'Orologio, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0004)
    From Album I, page 7
    Original negative number: 4
  - Basilica di St. Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-UN01)
    From Album I, page 8
    Original negative number: unknown
  - Porta di St. Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0003)
    From Album I, page 9
    Original negative number: 3
  - St. Marco Piazzetta, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0017)
    From Album I, page 10
    Original negative number: 17
  - St. Marco, No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0151)
    A negative number 00 is also present. From Album I, page 11
    Original negative number: 151
  - St. Marco, No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0202)
    From Album I, page 12
    Original negative number: 202
  - St. Marco, No. III, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-UN02)
    Historical caption label in French pasted on back of mount, with title, "Façade principale de la Basilique de Saint Marc." Small blind-stamp, "MSB" in lower right-hand corner of the print. From Album I, page 13
  - St. Marco, No. IV, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0047)
    Shows the four bronze horses. From Album I, page 14
    Original negative number: 47
  - Palazzo Ducale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0053)
    From Album I, page 15
    Original negative number: 53
  - Piazzetta San Giorgio Maggiore, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0096)
    From Album I, page 16
    Original negative number: 96
  - Palazzo Ducale, No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0038)
    From Album I, page 17
    Original negative number: 38
  - Palazzo Ducale, No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0019)
    From Album I, page 18
    Original negative number: 19
  - Palace / Bridge of Sighs / Prison, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-UN03)
    From Album I, page 19
  - Bridge of Sighs, No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0036)
    From Album I, page 20
    Original negative number: 36
  - Procuratie Nuove, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0130)
    From Album I, page 21
    Original negative number: 130
  - Piazzetta San Giorgio, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0109)
    From Album I, page 22
    Original negative number: 109
  - Winged Lion of St. Mark, circa 1860-1868 (Album 1, Print RL-11356-0157)
    From Album I, page 23
    Original negative number: 157
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na04)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." Signed "Co. Naya. 4". From Album II, page 1
    Original negative number: Na04
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na10)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 2
    Original negative number: Na10
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na02)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 3
    Original negative number: Na02
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na07)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 4
    Original negative number: Na07
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na08)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 5
    Original negative number: Na08
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na09)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 6
    Original negative number: Na09
  - Bassirilievi nella chiesa di SS. Giovanni e Paolo in Venezia, 1865 October (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na01)
    Subcaption: "Fotografie tratte dagli originali da C. Naya." From Album II, page 7
    Original negative number: Na01
  - The Adoration No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-Na05)
    Signed, "Co. Naya fat [fiat?] 5". From Album II, page 8
    Original negative number: Na05
  - The Adoration No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-UN04)
    Signed, "fa. Co. Naya". Continuation of the previous image, Adoration No. I. From Album II, page 9
  - Interno della Chiesa dei Gesuiti, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0139)
    From Album II, page 10
    Original negative number: 139
  - Coro della Chiesa di S. Giorgio, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0135)
    From Album II, page 11
    Original negative number: 135
  - Interno della Chiesa di S. Giovanni e Paolo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0137)
    From Album II, page 12
    Original negative number: 137
  - Porta principale di S. Giovanni di Paolo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0097)
    From Album II, page 13
    Original negative number: 97
  - Entrata della Chiesa dei Frari, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0211)
    Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari. From Album II, page 14
    Original negative number: 211
  - Monumento di Tiziano, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0073)
    Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari. From Album II, page 15
    Original negative number: 73
  - Monumento di Canova, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0074)
    Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari. From Album II, page 16
    Original negative number: 74
  - Monumento di Canova No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0127)
    Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari. From Album II, page 17
    Original negative number: 127
  - Monumento del Doge Vendramin, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0134)
    Basilica dei Santi Paolo e Giovanni. From Album II, page 18
    Original negative number: 134
  - Chiesa di S. Nicolo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0227)
    From Album II, page 19
    Original negative number: 227
  - Interno della Chiesa dei Greci, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0132)
    From Album II, page 20
    Original negative number: 132
  - Monumento del Doge Mocenigo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0138)
    Basilica dei Santi Paolo e Giovanni. From Album II, page 21
    Original negative number: 138
  - Altare Maggiore dei Scalzi, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0141)
    Santa Maria di Nazareth, also called Chiesa degli Scalzi. From Album II, page 22
    Original negative number: 141
  - Altare della Madonna del Rosario ai Scalzi, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0143)
    Santa Maria di Nazareth, also called Chiesa degli Scalzi. From Album II, page 23
    Original negative number: 143
  - Interno della Chiesa dei Frari, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0213)
    From Album II, page 24
    Original negative number: 213
  - Altare Maggiore dei Gesuiti, circa 1860-1868 (Album 2, Print RL-11356-0142)
    From Album II, page 25
    Original negative number: 142
  - Vestibolo di S. Marco No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0081)
    From Album III, page 1
    Original negative number: 81
  - Vestibolo di S. Marco No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0145)
    From Album III, page 2
    Original negative number: 145
  - Battistero di S. Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0128)
    From Album III, page 3
    Original negative number: 128
  - Porta del Sansovino, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0223)
    Basilica di S. Marco. From Album III, page 4
    Original negative number: 223
  - Altare Maggiore di S. Marco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0140)
    From Album III, page 5
    Original negative number: 140
  - Mosaico di S. Marco No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0058)
    From Album III, page 6
    Original negative number: 58
  - Mosaico di S. Marco No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0136)
    From Album III, page 7
    Original negative number: 136
  - Mosaico di S. Marco No. III, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0057)
    From Album III, page 8
    Original negative number: 57
  - Interno della Chiesa di S. Marco No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0131)
    From Album III, page 9
    Original negative number: 131
  - Interno della Chiesa di S. Marco No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0082)
    From Album III, page 10
    Original negative number: 82
  - Entrata del Palazzo Ducale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0005)
    From Album III, page 11
    Original negative number: 5
  - Scala dei Giganti, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0006)
    Palazzo Ducale, with two sculptures of Mars and Neptune by Sansovino. From Album III, page 12
    Original negative number: 6
  - Cortile del Palazzo Ducale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0051)
    From Album III, page 13
    Original negative number: 51
  - Dettaglio interno del Palazzo Ducale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0054)
    From Album III, page 14
    Original negative number: 54
  - Galleria del Palazzo No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0239)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 15
    Original negative number: 239
  - Galleria del Palazzo No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0243)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 16
    Original negative number: 243
  - Scala d'oro del Palazzo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0241)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 17
    Original negative number: 241
  - Entrata della Museo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-UN05)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 18
  - Museo del Palazzo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0204)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 19
    Original negative number: 204
  - Pozzo nel Cortile del Palazzo No. I, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0102)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 20
    Original negative number: 102
  - Pozzo nel Cortile del Palazzo No. II, circa 1860-1868 (Album 3, Print RL-11356-0099)
    Palazzo Ducale. From Album III, page 21
    Original negative number: 99
  - Palazzo Cavalli con la Chiesa della Salute sul Gran Canale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-UN06)
    From Album IV, page 1
  - Gran Canale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0070)
    From Album IV, page 2
    Original negative number: 70
  - Gondola Regina, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-UN07)
    From Album IV, page 3
  - Ponte Rialto, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-UN08)
    From Album IV, page 4
  - Palazzo sul Gran Canale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0013)
    From Album IV, page 5
    Original negative number: 13
  - Palazzo Foscari e Giustinian Vescovi, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0014)
    From Album IV, page 6
    Original negative number: 14
  - Gondola - Gran Canale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-UN09)
    There is a small "MSB" blind-stamped in the lower right corner. On the back of the mount is a historical caption in French, with the title "Piazzetta vue de la mer, Gondole Vénitienne." From Album IV, page 7
  - Palazzo Pesaro, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0020)
    From Album IV, page 8
    Original negative number: 20
  - Chiesa di Santa Maria della Salute, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0023)
    From Album IV, page 9
    Original negative number: 23
  - Chiesa dei Scalzi, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0066)
    From Album IV, page 10
    Original negative number: 66
  - Palazzo Mocenigo, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0194)
    From Album IV, page 11
    Original negative number: 194
  - Palazzo Grimani, Before 1866 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0072)
    Shield with Austrian Empire coat-of-arms on building reads "Direzione delle Poste." From Album IV, page 12
    Original negative number: 72
  - Palazzo Foscari, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0091)
    From Album IV, page 13
    Original negative number: 91
  - Palazzo Rezzonico, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0021)
    From Album IV, page 14
    Original negative number: 21
  - Palazzino, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0156)
    From Album IV, page 15
    Original negative number: 156
  - Interno della Chiesa dei San Rocco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0214)
    From Album IV, page 16
    Original negative number: 214
  - Bronze Gate - San Rocco, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0200)
    From Album IV, page 17
    Original negative number: 200
  - Pozzo dei Marmore, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0232)
    Rainwater well in the Campo Santi Giovanni e Paolo. From Album IV, page 18
    Original negative number: 232
  - Statua equestre di Bartolomeo Colleoni, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0034)
    From Album IV, page 19
    Original negative number: 34
  - Entrata del Arsenale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0010)
    From Album IV, page 20
    Original negative number: 10
  - Leone all'Arsenale, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0161)
    From Album IV, page 21
    Original negative number: 161
  - Scala Minelli, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0162)
    From Album IV, page 22
    Original negative number: 162
  - Monumento di Bartolomeo Colleoni, circa 1860-1868 (Album 4, Print RL-11356-0016)
    From Album IV, page 23
    Original negative number: 16